A Guide to the Records of the Charlottesville School Board 1869-2006
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series III: Correspondence
  - Correspondence City Improvements 1927
    - Correspondence School Board and City Council 1974-1976, 76 items (Box-folder 8:1)
      Correspondents include William J. Ellena, Francis H. Fife, Cole Hendrix, J. A. Kessler, the Reverend Henry B. Mitchell, Booker T. Reaves, Satyhendra Huja, Clarence McClure, and Alicia B. Lugo. Topics include land purchases; construction costs; a joint athletic stadium and new gymnasium; deed for Charlottesville High School; joint city-county council; city use of swimming pools and renovations at Buford and Walker schools; city maintenance of school athletic facilities; joint data processing; use of McGuffey, Lane and Jefferson schools; rental funds and fire safety at Lane; parking at McGuffey and map; capital projects; hiring of architects Stainback and Scribner; pupil transportation and Yellow Transit Company; board meeting minutes; unused funds; Region X; middle school program; and a conference on crime.
    - Correspondence School Board and City Council regarding the sale of Lane High School Building 1976-1978, 61 items (Box-folder 8:2)
      Correspondents mentioned are Francis H. Fife, George H. Gilliam, Cole Hendrix, Elizabeth A. Bowers, Dale R. Metcalf, William J. Ellena, Harry Porter, Richard L. Jennings, Nancy K. O'Brien, Fahy G. Mullaney,Thomas W. Branham, Cole Hendrix, W.P. Mitchell, Gerald E. Fisher, Carl Van Fossen, and T. Page Williams of Michael and Dent, LTD. Plans to allow Albemarle County Offices access to the Lane High School building in exchange for allowing the City access to the Burley School and the eventual sale of Lane. (See also Miscellaneous, Schools, Lane High School Box 66 Folder: 17))
    - Correspondence School Board and City Council 1977, 45 items (Box-folder 8:3)
      Correspondents include Dr. Charles William Hurt; Dr. William J. Ellena; Nancy K. O'Brien; Richard L. Jennings; Roger C. Wiley; C. Robert Stripling; Cole Hendrix; Booker Reaves, and William P. Mitchell. Topics mentioned are land grading, and school construction at Charlottesville High, Greenbrier, Clark, and Jackson-Via schools. Also mentioned are economic related items such as the consolidation of school and city functions; gas shortages; reduction of water use; salaries; capital projects; joint data processing system; economic development; community education; United Way campaign; lack of funds for a hearing program (Farley case); and an urban observatory report.
    - Correspondence School Board and City Council 1978--1980, 33 items (Box-folder 8:4)
      Correspondents include Dr. William J. Ellena, Richard L. Jennings, Laurence A. Brunton, Barbara B. Deaver, Cole Hendrix, William P. Mitchell; Jimmie J. Dunbar, James R. Boyd, Region Ten Community Home; Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr., and Francis L. Buck, Topics mentioned are a new auditorium, gym, and sports complex for Charlottesville, and repairs for Buford, and Walker schools, social security, retirement; budget; capital improvement; speech and hearing services (letter to Harry F. Byrd, Jr., Farley case;) inappropriate song "Suffocation;" audits; hiring; pupil to teacher ratio; salaries; Region Ten Property; enrollment; and All America City Banquet.
    - Correspondence School Board and City Council 1981-1982, 31 items (Box-folder 8:5)
      Correspondents include Cole Hendrix, Dr. William Ellena, Region Ten Community Services, Satyendra Singh Huja, Richard L. Jennings, Francis L. Buck, C. Robert Stripling, Thomas McLernon, Mitchell Van Yahres, Alicia B.Lugo, Gary B. O'Connell, Dr. Vincent C. Cibbarelli; Roger C. Wiley; Mark Krebs; Jimmie J. Dunbar, Robert Sheets and Adom, Inc. Topics mentioned are land sale, and school repairs at Charlottesville and Buford schools; Technical Education Center; city and school repairs; city and county consolidation; bus supervision; Region Ten property; reduction of water use; budget; federal budget cuts; capital improvements; salary increase for School Board members; Lane Football Field; and a data processing system.
    - Correspondence School Board and City Council 1983--1984, 23 items (Box-folder 9:1)
      Correspondents include Vincent Cibbarelli, Alicia B. Lugo, Francis L. Buck, Jimmie J. Dunbar, Dr. John Morris III, Mitchell Van Yahres,Tom McLernon, Robert Black, Myron E. Cale, Gary B. O'Connell, Dr. Joseph Mooney, and Cole Hendrix. Topics mentioned are building program (from 1967;) improvements for Charlottesville High School; asbestos removal; city staff to maintain school athletic fields; city and county coordination; budget; audit; capital improvements; aid grant; joint processing data system; phonics and look-say teaching methods; increase in salary for City School Board members and teachers.
    - Correspondence School Board and City Council 1985-1986, 33 items (Box-folder 9:2)
      Correspondents include Francis L. Buck, Alicia B. Lugo, Vincent Cibbarelli, Thomas McLernon, Gary B. O'Connell, Herbert R. Cottrill; Helen H. Poore; Richard D. Greig, Cole Hendrix, Attorney General Gerald L. Baliles, Alson H. Smith, Jr., Mitchell Van Yahres, Donald J. Finley, and Joseph Mooney. Topics included are use of Jefferson School; repairs and renovations for Clark, Venable, Jackson-Via, and Charlottesville High School; bus drivers strike; academic achievement; education, pupil transportation; School Board members term of office; student government; summer and after school programs; salaries; federal funding cuts; capital improvements; internal accounting; lawsuit (special education student;) teacher reference; and Bicentennial of the U. S. Constitution
    - Correspondence School Board and City Council 1987-1989, 13 items (Box-folder 9:3)
      Correspondents mentioned are Francis L. Buck, Elizabeth B. Waters, Vincent Cibbarelli, Richard D. Greig, Joseph Mooney, John L. Pezzoli, Cole Hendrix, and Monique Cardin. Topics include the basketball team; reorganization of the middle schools to balance minorities at Buford and Walker students; task force on youth; capital projects; budget; county students; French teacher; and a new smoking ordinance.
    - Correspondence School Board and City Council 1990-1995, 44 items (Box-folder 9:4)
      Elizabeth B. Waters; Joseph R. McGeehan; Alvin Edwards; Rauzelle J. Smith; Thomas J. Vandever; David J. Toscano; Linda S. Seaman; Dorothea M. Shannon; and John T. Casteen, III. Topics mentioned are Madison House; Piedmont Virginia Community College and the University of Virginia; salaries; the Performing Arts Center; Italian-American Educational Exchange Program; phonics; asbestos; gain sharing; achievement of African-American pupils; board meeting minutes; 7-Eleven stores commitment to literacy; Walker students; Albemarle County High School Feasibility Study; Tonsler Park; and the West Main Street revitalization project. There is also a letter from Alvin Edwards asking First Lady Barbara Bush to listen to a story written by a fifth grade student.
- Series IV: Facilities Management
  - A. Correspondence
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and architect Charles J. Calrow about the construction of McGuffey School 1913-1915, 6 items (Box-folder 9:5)
      Other correspondents mentioned are Charles M. Robinson, J. A. Burgess, Harmon & Walsh, C. W. Allen, Charlottesville Lumber Company, Ferguson, Calrow & Taylor, and Mayor Olivier. Topics include a purchase of The Rectory of the Episcopal Church; plans and bids for work on existing and new school buildings; overcrowding and repairs at [Midway School;] a conflict of interest with Charlottesville Lumber Company; a street car switch; and tension between Mayor Olivier and the School Board.
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson (about the purchase of land for Venable) 1913-1915, 22 items (Box-folder 9:6)
      Correspondents mentioned are J. H. Lindsay, James G. Johnson, Eugene Bradbury, J. E. Harrison, H. B. Lee, J. E. Early, and Thomas Carr. Topics include a resolution for a new high school; use of the Episcopal Rectory as a primary school; alterations to H. B. Lee's house; purchases of McKee Row and Patterson property; and minutes of the School Board.
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and architect Charles J. Calrow about the construction of McGuffey School 1916 January-March, 33 items (Box-folder 9:7)
      Some of the correspondence reveals that Dr. Johnson was very concerned about the subcontractor following his instructions on plastering and Mr. Calrow mediated between Dr. Johnson and the Charlottesville Lumber Company.
    - Oversize Sketch of Primary School Plan of Foundation and Base Angles 1916 April 13, 1 item
      American Blower Company detail of a fan
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and architect Charles J. Calrow about the construction of McGuffey School 1916 April-May, 65 items (Box-folder 9:8)
      Tensions continued between Dr. Johnson and the Charlottesville Lumber Company and caused delays in construction. There was also a discrepancy with quotes given by N. A. Murphy of the American Heating and Ventilation Company.
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and architect Charles J. Calrow about the construction of McGuffey School 1916 June-November, 95 items (Box-folder 10:1)
      Correspondents include W. R. Barksdale, Charlottesville Lumber Company, The Slatington Banger Slate Syndicate, American Blower Company, Mr. R. Smith, and Johnson Service Company. Dr. Johnson wrote to Mr. Calrow about the delays with the Charlottesville Lumber Company and his dissatisfaction with the stone work. (Papers are very fragile and torn).
    - Oversize Sketch of Retaining Wall for McGuffey Primary School n. d., 1 item
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and architect Charles J. Calrow about the plans for Venable School 1922, 34 items (Box-folder 10:2)
      There is a proposal from Dr. Johnson to locate the new school (Venable) on Fourteenth Street, hire Calrow as the architect and name the school Davis Primary School after Noah K. Davis, a highly respected teacher and follower of McGuffey. He also proposed to use Major Eugene Bradbury as the architect for the expansion of the "colored school." There is also a list of streets in Charlottesville.
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and Charles J. Calrow about the plans for Venable School 1923 January-March, 63 items (Box-folder 10:3)
      Correspondents mentioned James G. Johnson, Charles J. Calrow, Dr. Edwin Alderman, Major Eugene Bradbury, Miss Carrie Burnley, Miss Septima Moran, Mrs. Fred M. Alexander, Mrs. Huffman, and Linthicum & Linthicum Architects. Topics include land purchases, a bond issue and building Venable School; exhaustion for Dr. Johnson; a comment from Dr. Alderman that McGuffey was "one of the most beautiful buildings that he has ever seen;" recommendation of Major [Eugene] Bradbury as architect for the "colored school;" quote by Johnson that, "… wherever they may breathe the air; she [Miss Burnley]and Miss Moran both of whom have more instinct about what is right than any two women you can find..;" comment from Johnson, "Please do not say grammar school any more. Never use any other term than Primary School
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and Charles J. Calrow and plans for Venable School 1923 April-June, 53 items (Box-folder 10:4)
      Correspondents include James G. Johnson, Major John S. Graves, Charles J. Calrow, and the United States Radiator Corporation. Topics include the Charlottesville Charter; date of bidding process; allocation of funds; the building boycott; illness of Dr. Johnson's son; and Mr. McIntire's knowledge about architecture.
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and Charles J. Calrow and plans for Venable 1923 July-September, 26 items (Box-folder 10:5)
      There are letters about finalizing specifications and plans; waiting to hear from courts about the Charlottesville Charter; and delays due to a gasoline ordinance in which Richard E. Byrd [Admiral?] is mentioned.
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and Charles J. Calrow and plans for Venable 1924 January-February, 74 items (Box-folder 10:6)
      Correspondents include W. P. Thurston Company, Miller Engineering Corporation, Charlottesville Lumber Company; King Lumber Company, Graham Construction Company, W. L. Ragland Company, Burroughs & Mankin, Salem Brick Company, National Radiator Company, and Glasgow Clay Products Company. Topics include the Charlottesville Charter; the bond issue; references for Gooch-Williams Company who won the bid; copy of bid from McGuffey School; minutes of the School Board and city council; and specifications for heating and ventilation from Calrow.
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and Charles J. Calrow and construction of Venable School 1924 March 1-22, 42 items (Box-folder 10:7)
      Correspondents also include Raymond V. Long, and Major John Graves. Topics included are architect fees; construction details such as racking lumber, bricks, and latrine fixtures; state recommendations; bond form with job specifications; and an agreement between Gooch-Williams & Company and the School Board.
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and Charles J. Calrow and construction of Venable School 1924 March 24-31, 47 items (Box-folder 11:1)
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and Charles J. Calrow and construction of Venable School 1924 April-May, 113 items (Box-folder 11:2)
      Correspondents mentioned are William H. Wood; Major John Graves; and John Newcomb. Topics included are building details such as the foundation, defects in concrete walls, latrine fixtures, panic bolts, ditches, sand, cost of dirt, chipped stones, and removal of trees and stumps; the strike; "Negroes" and Jefferson Day excitement;" a quote from Johnson, "… no one could depend upon its being done right unless some expert like you [Calrow] or Professor Newcomb stood right over it every minute.
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and Charles J. Calrow 1924 June-July, 57 items (Box-folder 11:3)
      Correspondents included are Gooch-Williams & Co., Mr. Cabaniss; Salem Brick Company, Reading Iron Company, L. T. Hanckel & Sons, Lacy & Barnett, American Blower Co., and Linthicum & Linthicum. Topics include repair for a concrete wall, and a refund from a land purchase.
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and Charles J. Calrow and construction of Venable 1924 August-October, 101 items (Box-folder 11:4)
      Correspondents mentioned are Mr. Cabiniss, Mr. Milner, Raymond V. Long, Lacy & Barnett, Mr. Warrick, Mr. Dyer, Economy Concrete Co. of Virginia, Williams Slate Co., Gooch-Williams, W. T. Martin Hardware Company, and L. T. Hanckel & Sons. Topics include Johnson's complaints about the "slipshod" construction work being done and efforts by Calrow to reassure Johnson; insurance on the building; hiring a watchman; and "Negro" gambling.
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and Charles J. Calrow and Venable construction) 1924 Nov-Dec, 63 items (Box-folder 11:5)
      Correspondents mentioned are Lacy & Barnett, Thom Plastering, Gooch & Williams, W. T. Martin Hardware Company, Dr. Watson, [Harris Hank,] J. Y. Gooch & Company, W. H. Wood, [Milner,] Lacy & Barnett, Toch Brothers, James F. Minor, W. T. Martin Hardware Company, The Corbin Company, Salem Brick Company and R. L. Alexander Co. Topics included are the death of School Board member Dr. Watson; new school for "colored" children; hedging and plantings at Midway School; complaints about Lacy & Barnett; dissatisfaction with the plastering; payments; insurance; and minutes of the School Board.
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and Charles J. Calrow 1925 Jan-April, 112 items (Box-folder 11:6)
      Correspondents mentioned are United States Gypsum Company, Gooch-Williams & Company, Lacy & Barnett, Eugene Bradbury, H. A. Yancey, [Mitchell,] Flavin & Watson Co., Inc., G. M. Pierce, A. C. Dyer & Company, Hall & Mitchell, R. L. Alexander, Co., Raymond V. Long, and The H. B. Smith Co., Topics included the mounting frustration of Johnson, and further attempts of Calrow to reassure him about the complaints (serious cracking in the plaster; drinking problem of Mr. Barnett, who had to be fired. Calrow wrote, "Barnett has been drinking so much that he hardly knows what he has been doing for two months.") Other topics include payment for drawings of changes to Jefferson School and grading of the Venable Athletic Field.
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and Charles J. Calrow 1925 May-December, 32 items (Box-folder 12:1)
      Correspondents mentioned are Dr. Edwin Alderman, Gooch-Williams & Company, Hall & Mitchell, Raymond Long, and Mottley Construction Company. Topics include a comment by Dr. Alderman that Venable was "the handsomest one in or about Charlottesville;" exhaustion of Johnson; alterations of the "Negro School;" payments; unsatisfactory night watchman; poor stone work, plastering, and leaks at Venable.
    - Oversize sketches by Charles J. Calrow showing discrepancies in playfield measurements. 1925 August 14, 1 letter and 2 sketches
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and Charles J. Calrow 1926, 17 items (Box-folder 12:2)
      Correspondents included are Gooch-Williams & Company, W. L. Lacy, and Glauber Brass Mf'g. Co. Topics mentioned are land purchased for additions to Jefferson School, and warrants for final payments. There is also a blue print sketch of the proposed sewer at Venable.
    - Oversize Architectural drawings by Calrow including fire escape stairs at Primary School Building [Midway] and other drawings of "Midway" n. d., 14 items
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and Charles J. Calrow 1927-1928, 38 items (Box-folder 12:3)
      Correspondents mentioned are Lee H. Williamson, Allan J. Saville, C. P. Walston, L. F. Shelburne, J. H. Saunders, Henry G. Ellis, H. A. Hunt, H. C. Bowton, W. H. Kester, G.L. H. Johnson, Roy C. Bowers, T. J. Collins & Son, C. H. Hinnant, Stanislaw J. Makielski, E. W. Spence, L. O. Freeman, Jr., and Wyatt C. Wood. Topics include estimates for a new high school building [Lane;] School Board minutes, sewer survey; zoning contract; questionnaires answered from Virginia School Superintendents about their school buildings; architects interested in bids; and inspection of Midway School.
    - Included with correspondence are articles by Dr. Johnson about school projects 1927, 50 items (Box-folder 12:3a)
    - Correspondence James G. Johnson and Charles J. Calrow and plans for George Rogers Clark School 1929, 109 items (Box-folder 12:4)
      Correspondents included are Raymond V. Long, L.O. Freeman, Jr., W. J. and Lillie F. Harvey, B. G. and Kathleen Payne, Lloyd M and Annie L. Haggard, C. E. and Janie W. Crawford, D. W. and Willie M. Godwin, B. S. and Bettie J. Young, C. G. and Nannie Blake Jones, Major John Graves, J. A. Zurn Mfg. Co.; Old Virginia Brick; A. Y. McDonald Mfg. Co.; E. T. Mankin, Incorporated; Fulton Brick Works; U. S. Radiator Corporation; National Radiator Corporation; Covington Brick Company; Staunton Brick Company; Glasgow Brick Company; Salem Brick Company; and Locher & Co., Inc.. Topics include land purchases; inspection of Midway School; estimate on the cost of a new high school building; an extension of Market Street from Second Street Northwest to connect into Preston Avenue at the foot of Beck's Hill and right of way through McGuffey; bond issue for a new elementary school [George Rogers Clark;] blue prints and plans for Clark School; references for contractors; and minutes of the School Board regarding Clark School.
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and Charles J. Calrow and construction of George Rogers Clark School 1930 January-February, 105 items (Box-folder 12:5)
      Correspondents included are mostly bidders for constructing the new school, H. M. Wilson, The Wilson Company; Charlottesville Lumber Company; Doyle & Russell; J. F. Barbour & Sons; J. C. Curtis; Davis Brothers; Failes-Burrage Construction Company; James Fox & Sons; W. T. Gregory; Frank E. Hartman Company; Harrisonburg Building and Supply Company; J. R. Jones & Conquest; Harwood Construction Company; Miller Engineering Corporation; North-Eastern Construction Company; J. T. Nuckols; Wise Granite & Construction Company; Alberene Stone Company, W. P. Thurston, The Thurston Company, Inc., Miller Engineering Corporation, P. E. W. Goodwin, J. W. Atkinson, Fuqua Construction Company, and Claiborne & Taylor Construction. Also included are Raymond V. Long, The Builders Exchange of Richmond, E. T. Mankin, Inc., Virginia Building Material, Co., Inc., Old Virginia Brick Company, J. A. Zurn Mfg. Co., A. Y. McDonald Mgr. Co., and United States Radiator Corporation. Topics include specifications and prints for Clark; and interest in the bidding process.
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and Charles J. Calrow 1930 March, 130 items (Box-folder 12:6)
      Correspondents mentioned are the W.P. Thurston Company, The Wilson Company, and the Harrisonburg Building and Supply Company. Topics include the award of the contract to The Wilson Company; concerns by contractors about the bidding process; minutes from a School Board meeting regarding the bids; bids of all the contractors and a contract agreement with The Wilson Company; references for the bidding contractors and subcontractors, and a list of supplies that the Wilson Company would need to begin their work.
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and Charles J. Calrow about the construction of George Rogers Clark School 1930 April-May, 62 items (Box-folder 12:7)
      Correspondents mentioned are The Wilson Company, Virginia Alberene Corporation, Economy Concrete Company, D. A. Ebinger, Sanitary MFG. Co., Mirabella & Sons, Standard Iron Works, and the Virginia Steel Company. Topics include schedules, costs of supplies and labor; plans and details of the construction of windows, stairs and stonework; and a requisition for payment to the Wilson Company. There is one sketch of a floor plan in the coal room.
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and Charles J. Calrow 1930 June-December, 112 items (Box-folder 13:1)
      Correspondents mentioned are W. F. Carter, Jr., The Young Men's Business Club, The Wilson Company, W. Allan Perkins, the Charlottesville Hardware Company, W. T. Martin Hardware Company, Sensibaugh-Ritchie Electric Company, Yale & Towne Mgf. Co., The Century Brass Works, S. Mirabella & Sons, Failes & Burrage, Shelby Spring Hinge Co., The Barrett Company, National Gypsum Company, Thomas Moulding Floor Company, W. L. Lacy, and Metrolite Manufacturing Co. Topics include receipts, requisitions; a report that alleged that out of town sub-contractors were always selected over local businesses; and a blue print for the Market Street expansion. Johnson and Calrow also discussed work that was being done on Dr. Johnson's house.
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and architect Charles J. Calrow 1931 January-March, 50 items (Box-folder 13:2)
      Correspondents include W. L. Lacy, The Wilson Company, S. Mirabella & Sons, Failes-Burrage Construction Company, Thomas Moulding Floor Company, J. A. Burgess, and C. E. Chisholm. Topics include near completion of Clark School; the beauty of Venable School; receipts and a claim against the School Board and the Mirabella & Sons for payment due to the Failes-Burrage Construction Company.
    - Correspondence Superintendent James G. Johnson and architect Charles J. Calrow 1931 April-June, 50 items (Box-folder 13:3)